Francisco Nunes

Born: December 20, 1987—Porto, Portugal Nationality: Portuguese & Brazilian

Phone: +351 919 671 364

Email: francisco.nunes@fraunhofer.pt

Scholar: https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=D2rDc98AAAAJ

Twitter: @xico_nunes

Research interests

I am interested in learning about people and how they use technology. My projects are usually at the intersection of computer science, medicine, design, and social sciences. I am an expert in ethnographically informed design, user-centred design, and participatory design approaches.

Broad keywords for my work would be: HCI, CSCW, Medical/Health informatics, Ambient assisted living, and Science and Technology Studies.

Education

2012-2017 PHD in Human-Computer Interaction, TU Wien

Thesis: "The Everyday Life with Parkinson's and Self-care Technologies". Supervised by

Geraldine Fitzpatrick.

2005-2010 MSc/BSc in Informatics and Computing Engineering, University of Porto

Thesis: "Healthcare TV Based User Interfaces for Older Adults". Supervised by Paula Alexan-

dra Silva and Teresa Galvão.

Experience

2017-now	Senior researcher, Fraunhoter Portugal AlCOS, Porto
2016-2017	Researcher, NOVA-LINCS, Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Lisboa
2012-2017	PhD Student, Institute for Design and Assessment of Technology, TU Wien, Vienna
2010-2012	Researcher, Fraunhofer Portugal AICOS, Porto
2008-2010	Research Assistant, Fraunhofer Portugal AICOS, Porto

Grants, honours & awards

Acquired project grants

"Smartphones for Smart Seniors - S₄S" funded by ANI (Portugal) − €137K Lead proposal writer and co-PI at AICOS.

"REMPARK" funded by FP7-ICT (EU) – €411k 2011 Co-proposal writer, workpackage manager and co-investigator at AICOS. "CellPipe UI" funded by Alcatel-Lucent – €49k 2011 Co-proposal writer and co-investigator at AICOS. OTHER GRANTS AND HONOURS Two special recognitions for an 'Excellent Review' at CHI 2016 2016 Grant for attending conference from TU Wien (€1390) 2016 Grant for attending CHI 2015 doctoral consortium (\$1300) 2015 Vienna PhD School of Informatics scholarship (3 years of funding) 2012 Dance! Don't Fall was on the Top-25 Apps, CES Mobile Apps Showdown 2012 Smart Companion was 2nd most creative app, ZON Creativity Award (prize: €6250) 2011 Mover was 5th best Lifestyle app, Android Developer Challenge II (prize: equipment) 2010 Teaching $\dot{\sigma}$ supervision experience Courses Summer 2015 HCI in Healthcare (MSc) - Co-teaching and supervision of student projects in Vienna User Research Methods (MSc) - Co-teaching and supervision of student projects in Vienna Winter 2014 SUPERVISED STUDENTS Martin Herndl (BSc TU Wien) - Developing an Android Self-Management Application for 2015 People with Parkinson's Disease. Co-supervised with Geraldine Fitzpatrick. João Cevada (MSc FEUP/ AICOS) – User Interface Design Recommendations for Fitting 2012 Smartphone Applications to Persons With Parkinson. Co-supervised with Luís Teixeira. **Projects** *Clockwork* (EU AAL-JP) – This project developed technologies to support the self-reflection 2014-2018 and self-awareness of shift workers. I lead the research team of Fraunhofer, supervising the user research, design, and evaluation of the smartphone app and the smart badge. I also coordinated the project more generally. http://clockworkproject.eu/ REMPARK (EU ICT-FP7) – This four year project developed a wearable system to monitor 2011-2015 symptoms of people with Parkinson's, intervene in the gait, and collect data to improve the therapy. I participated in the first year of the project and was involved in user research and early design phases of the smartphone apps for patients. http://www.rempark.eu/ S4S (PT) – This project adapted the Windows Phone for older adults. I participated in the 2011-2014 first year of the project and was involved in the user research, design, and evaluation of

Dance! Don't Fall (Internal) - This project created an Android application that monitors

the risk of falling while actively reducing it through dancing. I participated in the user research, design, and evaluation of the application. http://dancedontfall.projects.fraunhofer.pt

some of the smartphone applications.

2011-2012

Smart Companion (Internal) – This project created an Android Operating system specifically for older people. I participated in the user research, design, and evaluation of the smartphone applications. Smart Companion is today being sold by GOCIETY under the name GOLIVEPHONE. http://smartcompanion.projects.fraunhofer.pt

eCAALYX (EU AAL-JP) – This project created a telehealth system for older adults with chronic conditions. I participated in the the user research, design, and evaluation of the TV interfaces for older adults. http://ecaalyx.org

Mover (Internal) – This project created an Android app that explored the accelerometer to capture activity and thus promote movement. I participated in the design and evaluation of the app. Mover is today being sold as part of the GOLIVEPHONE mentioned above. http://mover.projects.fraunhofer.pt/

Service

PROGRAM COMMITTEE MEMBER

2016	Mindcare 2016
2016	PervasiveHealth 2016
2015	PervasiveHealth 2015
	And several workshops:
2016	Advances in DIY Health & Wellbeing at CHI '16
2014	Collaboration and Coordination in the Context of Informal Care Workshop at GROUP '14
2013	2nd Workshop on Computer Mediated Social Offline Interactions at Ubicomp '13

Workshop organizer

Workshop on Engineering Healthcare Technologies for Broadening the Participation of Patients and Carers

2015 Doctoral Colloquium of the Institute for Design and Assessment of Technology

Designing Self-care for Everyday Life at NordiCHI '14 (link)

Design Culture for Ageing Well Workshop at SouthCHI '13

Designing Systems for Health and Entertainment: what are we missing? at ACE '14 (link)

Summer Camp of the Institute for Design and Assessment of Technology

Reviewer

2013

2014

2013

Health Informatics Journal, IJHCS, IxD&A, JAMIA, JCSCW, Entertainment Computing, TOCHI.

CHI ('17, '16, '15, '14), CSCW ('17, '16, '15), Group '16, Healthcom '13, NordiCHI ('16, '14), PervasiveHealth ('17, '16, '15).

STUDENT VOLUNTEER

CHI ('16, '13), CSCW '15 PC meeting, NordiCHI '10

Publications & talks

H-index: 9; citations: 213 (source Google Scholar as at 08/2017)

PROCEEDINGS AND SPECIAL ISSUES EDITED

- P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, eds. (2016) "Special issue on fun and engaging computing technologies for health", *Entertainment Computing*, 15: 41–70
- N. Verdezoto, F. Nunes, E. Grönvall, G. Fitzpatrick, C. Storni, and M. Kyng, eds. (2015) "Proceedings of Designing Self-care for Everyday Life. Workshop in conjunction with NordiCHI 2014, 27th October 2014, Helsinki, Finland", *DAIMI Report Series*, 41(597).
- N. Verdezoto, F. Nunes, G. Fitzpatrick, and E. Grönvall, eds. (2014) "Designing Self-Care For Everyday Life", *Interaction Design and Architecture(s) Journal IxD&A*, 23: 142–190.

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- F. Nunes, T. Andersen, and G. Fitzpatrick (2017) "The agency of patients and carers in medical care and self-care technologies for interacting with doctors", *Health Informatics Journal*, 1–20.
- F. Güldenpfennig, F. Nunes, and G. Fitzpatrick (2016) "Making Space to Engage: An Openended Exploration of Technology Design with Older Adults", *International Journal of Mobile Human Computer Interaction*, 8(2): 1–19.
- F. Nunes, P. A. Silva, J. Cevada, A. C. Barros, L. Teixeira (2015) "User Interface Design Guidelines for Smartphone Applications for People With Parkinson's Disease", *Universal Access in the Information Society*, 15(4): 659–679.
- F. Nunes, N. Verdezoto, G. Fitzpatrick, M. Kyng, E. Grönvall, and C. Storni (2015) "Self-care Technologies in HCI: Trends, Tensions, and Opportunities", *ACM Transactions on Computer Human Interaction*, 22(6), article 33: 1–45.
- F. Nunes, and G. Fitzpatrick (2015) "Self-care Technologies and Collaboration", *International Journal of Human Computer Interaction*, 31(12): 869–881.
- A. Aguiar, F. Nunes, M. Silva, P. A. Silva, and D. Elias (2012) "Leveraging electronic ticketing to provide personalised navigation in a public transport network", *Intelligent Transportation Systems Transactions and Magazine*, 13(1): 213–220.

CONFERENCE PAPERS (PEER-REVIEWED)

- F. Güldenpfennig, Ö.Subasi, F. Nunes, M. Urbanek (2017) "UbiKit: Learning to Prototype for Tangible and Ubiquitous Computing", 31st British Human Computer Interaction Conference
- F. Güldenpfennig, F. Nunes, and G. Fitzpatrick (2015) "Proxycare: Integrating informal care into formal settings", in *Proc. of PervasiveHealth* 2015, 141–144.
- P. Jordan, P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, and R. Oliveira (2013) "mobileWAY A System to Reduce the Feeling of Temporary Lonesomeness of Persons with Dementia and to Foster Intercaregiver Collaboration", in *Proc. of HICSS* 2013, 2474–2483.
- P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, A. Vasconcelos, M. Kerwin, R. Moutinho, and P. Teixeira (2013) "Using the Smartphone Accelerometer to Monitor Fall Risk While Playing a Game: The Design

- and Usability Evaluation of Dance! Don't Fall", in Proc. of HCII 2013, 754-763.
- F. Nunes, M. Kerwin, and P. A. Silva (2012) "Design Recommendations for TV User Interfaces for Older Adults: Findings From the eCAALYX Project", in *Proc. of ASSETS 2012*, 41–48.
- M. Kerwin, F. Nunes, and P. A. Silva (2012) "Dance Don't Fall Preventing Falls and Promoting Exercise at Home", in *Proc. of pHealth* 2012, 254–259.
- A. Vasconcelos, P. A. Silva, J. Caseiro, F. Nunes, and L. F. Teixeira (2012) "Designing Tablet-based Games for Seniors: the Example of Cogniplay, a Cognitive Gaming Platform", in *Proc. of Fun & Games* 2012, 1–10.
- P. A. Silva, and F. Nunes (2010) "3 x 7 Usability Testing Guidelines for Older Adults", in *Proc. MEXIHC* 2010, 2: 1–8.
- F. Nunes, P. A. Silva, and F. Abrantes (2010) "Human-Computer Interaction and the Older Adult: an Example Using User Research and Personas", in *Proc. of PETRA 2010*, 49: 1–8.

POSTERS AND EXTENDED ABSTRACTS (PEER-REVIEWED)

- T. Marques, F. Nunes, P. A. Silva, and R. Rodrigues (2011) "Tangible Interaction on Tabletops for Elderly People", in *Proc. ICEC 2011*, pp. 440--443.
- T. Sousa, P. Tenreiro, P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, and E. Rodrigues (2011) "Cross-platform social web application for older adults with html 5", in *Proc. ICEC 2011*, pp. 375–378.

Position papers (juried)

- P. A. Silva, F. Nunes (2016) "Preface for the special issue on fun and engaging computing technologies for health", in *Entertainment Computing*, 15: 41–42.
- F. Nunes (2016) "The medication reminder as enforcing a medicalised perspective on daily life", in *Book of abstracts of the 6th STS Italia Conference*, 58.
- F. Nunes (2015) "Designing Self-care Technologies for Everyday Life: A Practice Approach", in *Proc. of CHI EA 2015*, 215–218.
- N. Verdezoto, F. Nunes, G. Fitzpatrick, E. Grönvall (2014) "Preface to the Focus Section", in *Interaction Design and Architecture(s) Journal IxD&A*, 23.
- F. Nunes (2013) "Improving the Self-care of Parkinson's Through Ubiquitous Computing", in *Proc. of Ubicomp Adjunct 2013*.
- F. Nunes and, P. A. Silva (2011) "The Smartphone A Mobile Companion for Older Adults", in *Proc. of Promoting and Supporting Healthy Living by Design Workshop at INTERACT 2011*, 41–43.
- P. M. Teixeira, P. A. Silva, F. Nunes, and L. F. Teixeira (2011) "Mover Activity Monitor and Fall Detector for Android", in *Proc. of Mobile Wellness Workshop at MobileHCI 2011*.
- F. Nunes, and P. A. Silva (2010) "Fostering Wellness of Older Adults While Performing Usability Testing", in *Proc. of HCI4WELL Workshop at HCI2010*.
- A. Aguiar, F. Nunes, M. Silva, and D. Elias (2009) "Personal Navigator for a Public Transport System Using RFID Ticketing", in *Proc. of inMotionog Workshop at Pervasive 2009*.

INVITED PRESENTATIONS

12/09/2017

"Self-care technologies" at the course Qualitative methods and co-design of self-care technologies of University of Copenhagen, Denmark.

"Self-care technologies" at the course Qualitative methods and co-design of self-care technologies of University of Copenhagen, Denmark.

"Understanding and Promoting the Creation of Patient Knowledge Online" at University of Trento & FBK, Italy.

"How can technology help people improve their self-care? Supporting engagement in their clinical consultations" at IT University of Copenhagen, Denmark.

"Designing Self-care Technology for People with Parkinson's: A Focus on Everyday Life"

"Designing Self-care Technology for People with Parkinson's: A Focus on Everyday Life" at University of Copenhagen, Denmark.

"The Self-care of Parkinson's" at the Designing Self-care for Everyday Life Workshop at NordiCHI 2014 in Helsinki, Finland.

"Design recommendations for TV user interfaces for older adults" at the Interactive Assistive Technologies for the Elderly Workshop in University of Aveiro, Portugal.

 $_{06/05/2011}$ "eCAALYX project" at the course Multimodal Interfaces of University of Porto, Portugal.

MEDIA MENTIONS

Mover was mentioned in the Jornal de Negócios (30/04/2010) and Diário de Notícias (29/05/2010). Smart Companion was described in RTP (01/08/2011), Porto Canal, and another time at Porto Canal (26/07/2012) when I was even interviewed.

Languages

Portuguese – native English – proficient Spanish – fluent French – intermediate (DELF A4 certificate) German – intermediate (B1.1 certificate)

References

Geraldine Fitzpatrick, TU Wien (geraldine.fitzpatrick@tuwien.ac.at)
Paula Alexandra Silva, National University of Ireland in Maynooth (palexa@gmail.com)

Last updated: September 14, 2017